<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>SCADAsploit</title>
    <link>https://scadasploit.dev/</link>
    <description>Recent content on SCADAsploit</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 May 2023 18:14:13 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://scadasploit.dev/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Contact</title>
      <link>https://scadasploit.dev/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://scadasploit.dev/contact/</guid>
      <description>SCADAsploit is developed by Omar Morando If you have any questions or queries about the product, feel free to reach us on the below contact and we will get back to you as soon as possible. SCADAsploit info: info@scadasploit.dev SCADAsploit OT Trainings: training@scadasploit.dev You can follow Omar’s tweets at @OmarMorando on twitter.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Experiences</title>
      <link>https://scadasploit.dev/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://scadasploit.dev/about/</guid>
      <description>Head of OT Cybersecurity &amp;amp; Innovation Lab (01/2023 - present) Sababa Security
Recent events are highlighting even more how Cybersecurity in the OT world is developing into one of the most fundamental areas in the field, especially when it comes to the protection of critical infrastructures and strategic industrial sites. • After having matured 20+ years of experience in PLC and SCADA systems, I have now taken up the leadership of Sababa&amp;rsquo;s OT Cybersecurity, with particular focus on the ICS, Automotive and Industrial IoT sectors.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Workshop</title>
      <link>https://scadasploit.dev/workshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://scadasploit.dev/workshop/</guid>
      <description>Head of OT Cybersecurity &amp;amp; Innovation Lab (01/2023 - present) Sababa Security
Recent events are highlighting even more how Cybersecurity in the OT world is developing into one of the most fundamental areas in the field, especially when it comes to the protection of critical infrastructures and strategic industrial sites. • After having matured 20+ years of experience in PLC and SCADA systems, I have now taken up the leadership of Sababa&amp;rsquo;s OT Cybersecurity, with particular focus on the ICS, Automotive and Industrial IoT sectors.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SCADAsploit module: Modbus Payload Transfer</title>
      <link>https://scadasploit.dev/posts/2022/04/scadasploit-module-modbus-payload-transfer/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Apr 2022 15:09:35 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://scadasploit.dev/posts/2022/04/scadasploit-module-modbus-payload-transfer/</guid>
      <description>The second module we are going to explore is called &amp;ldquo;Modbus Payload Transfer&amp;rdquo; and belongs to the auxiliary category.
What is it for The &amp;ldquo;Modbus Payload Transfer&amp;rdquo; module is a script that allows you to store and retrieve a payload/shellcode in the &amp;ldquo;holding registers&amp;rdquo; of a PLC via the Modbus TCP protocol. There are many PLCs exposed to the Internet, with this module it is possible to exploit their memory to upload a payload (shellcode/malware) so that it can be recovered at a later time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SCADAsploit module: Modbus Scan</title>
      <link>https://scadasploit.dev/posts/2022/04/scadasploit-module-modbus-scan/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Apr 2022 15:09:35 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://scadasploit.dev/posts/2022/04/scadasploit-module-modbus-scan/</guid>
      <description>Let&amp;rsquo;s get to know SCADAsploit a little better starting from one of the auxiliary modules present: Modbus Scan.
Position ourselves in the folder where we installed SCADAsploit and start it using the command $ ./scadasploit.py. Following the same approach philosophy of Metasploit, we can search for all modules that contain a keyword using the search &amp;lt;keyword&amp;gt; command or display the complete list of modules present with the show modules command.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SCADAsploit Framework</title>
      <link>https://scadasploit.dev/posts/2022/04/scadasploit-framework/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Apr 2022 15:09:35 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://scadasploit.dev/posts/2022/04/scadasploit-framework/</guid>
      <description>This section is dedicated to SCADAsploit, a framework I&amp;rsquo;m working on dedicated to OT/ICS penetration testing. You ask yourself: &amp;ldquo;But isn&amp;rsquo;t Metasploit already doing this?&amp;rdquo;. Certain! So what is the need to create a new tool like this? I try to give some answers:
framework exclusively dedicated to vulnerabilities of SCADA, PLC and other ICS devices written in Python, both the core of the framework and the modules &amp;ldquo;Metasploit like&amp;rdquo; interface greater focus on the installed PLC fleet, especially in Europe.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hacking: Stuxnet-like attack on a Modicon PLC</title>
      <link>https://scadasploit.dev/posts/2021/07/hacking-stuxnet-like-attack-on-a-modicon-plc/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jul 2021 15:09:35 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://scadasploit.dev/posts/2021/07/hacking-stuxnet-like-attack-on-a-modicon-plc/</guid>
      <description>Airbus CyberSecurity researchers recently demonstrated that hackers could launch an attack in Stuxnet-style against Schneider Electric&amp;rsquo;s Modicon programmable logic controllers (PLCs), but it is believed that products from other vendors could also be vulnerable to the same type of attack.
How does it work The infamous malware Stuxnet, which the United States and Israel used to damage the nuclear program Iranian, was designed to target the SIMATIC S7-300 and S7-400 PLCs manufactured by Siemens.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hacking: Pentest on a PLC</title>
      <link>https://scadasploit.dev/posts/2021/07/hacking-pentest-on-a-plc/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Jul 2021 15:09:35 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://scadasploit.dev/posts/2021/07/hacking-pentest-on-a-plc/</guid>
      <description>Penetration Test on a PLC Protecting an ICS environment, including PLCs, is not trivial, as these systems are not designed to be resilient to cyber attacks. This means that you have to somehow integrate cybersecurity resilience measures inside and around the ICS. Such measures include, for example:
perimeter protection, such as firewalls to reduce the risk of unwanted network traffic; network monitoring - preferably non-intrusive, ICS-specific, anomaly-based monitoring so as not to create any additional load on ICS networks; endpoint protection and monitoring to reduce the exposure of PLCs to attacks via remote connections.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hacking: attacking a PLC with Stuxnet</title>
      <link>https://scadasploit.dev/posts/2021/07/hacking-attacking-a-plc-with-stuxnet/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jul 2021 15:09:35 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://scadasploit.dev/posts/2021/07/hacking-attacking-a-plc-with-stuxnet/</guid>
      <description>To illustrate how a PLC can be attacked and what the consequences might be, let&amp;rsquo;s look at the Stuxnet worm.;
Introduction to Stuxnet Stuxnet is an independent worm, intended only for Siemens Supervisory Control and Data Acquisition (SCADA) systems. The worm was designed to attack specific Siemens PLCs and exploited four 0-day vulnerabilities. The final version of Stuxnet was first discovered in Belarus in June 2010 by Sergey Ulasen from Kaspersky Labs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hacking: Modbus TCP simulation in Linux</title>
      <link>https://scadasploit.dev/posts/2021/07/hacking-modbus-tcp-simulation-in-linux/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jul 2021 15:09:35 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://scadasploit.dev/posts/2021/07/hacking-modbus-tcp-simulation-in-linux/</guid>
      <description>ICS systems use many different protocols to communicate than standard IT systems. The most used standard is the Modbus protocol. Developed for the first time by Modicon (now Schneider Electric) in 1979 as a serial protocol, it has been modified and updated to work on an Ethernet TCP network, assuming the name of Modbus TCP. Below you can see a diagram summarizing the RTU (serial) packet structure and the TCP one.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
