<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>modbus on SCADAsploit</title>
    <link>https://scadasploit.dev/tags/modbus/</link>
    <description>Recent content in modbus on SCADAsploit</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 08 Jul 2021 15:09:35 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://scadasploit.dev/tags/modbus/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Hacking: Modbus TCP simulation in Linux</title>
      <link>https://scadasploit.dev/posts/2021/07/hacking-modbus-tcp-simulation-in-linux/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jul 2021 15:09:35 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://scadasploit.dev/posts/2021/07/hacking-modbus-tcp-simulation-in-linux/</guid>
      <description>ICS systems use many different protocols to communicate than standard IT systems. The most used standard is the Modbus protocol. Developed for the first time by Modicon (now Schneider Electric) in 1979 as a serial protocol, it has been modified and updated to work on an Ethernet TCP network, assuming the name of Modbus TCP. Below you can see a diagram summarizing the RTU (serial) packet structure and the TCP one.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hacking: Modbus</title>
      <link>https://scadasploit.dev/posts/2021/07/hacking-modbus/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jul 2021 15:09:35 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://scadasploit.dev/posts/2021/07/hacking-modbus/</guid>
      <description>One of the challenges of pentesting in the OT/ICS environment is given by the protocols used which can also be very different from those of IT. ICS installations use a wide variety of protocols that often have little in common with standard Ethernet and TCP/IP. This difference has been the strong point of OT installations for years, protecting them through the mechanism of &amp;ldquo;security by obscurity&amp;rdquo;. Now that these protocols are becoming more known and understood, security concerns in these facilities have been heightened.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
